<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The church-papist (so-called), his religion and tenets fully discovered in a serious dispute ... whereby the common ... arguments of pretended visibility, succession, universality, &amp;c., of the Roman Church ... are briefly confuted : whereunto is added, a short discourse proving episcopacy to be of divine institution, kingly government of Gods setting up, and the religion of the Church of England, to be the best in the world / by one of the children of the late captivity, 1680.</title>
            <author>Underwood, John, fl. 1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64702</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing U46</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7367</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13099623</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13099623</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97402</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64702)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97402)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 402:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The church-papist (so-called), his religion and tenets fully discovered in a serious dispute ... whereby the common ... arguments of pretended visibility, succession, universality, &amp;c., of the Roman Church ... are briefly confuted : whereunto is added, a short discourse proving episcopacy to be of divine institution, kingly government of Gods setting up, and the religion of the Church of England, to be the best in the world / by one of the children of the late captivity, 1680.</title>
                  <author>Underwood, John, fl. 1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Hartford ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: John Underwood.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: upper margin cropped, some text illegible with print show-through.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97402:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97402:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Church-Papiſt (SO CALLED;) HIS RELIGION AND TENETS Fully Diſcovered: IN A ſerious Diſpute, which long ſince happened between a (then) reputed Papiſt and an open profeſſed Romaniſt, whereby the common (and trite) Arguments of pretended Viſibility, Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, Univerſality, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the Roman Church, Travelling the Nation to amuſe and ſtagger the Weak, and to ſeduce and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the unſtable ſort of People, are briefly Confuted. WHEREUNTO IS ADDED, A ſhort Diſcourſe, Proving Epiſcopacy to be of Divine Inſtitution, King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Government of Gods ſetting up, and the Religion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to be the beſt in the World. <hi>By one of the Children of the late Captivity,</hi> 1680.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Hartford,</hi> at the Angel in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> near the <hi>Royal Exchange.</hi> 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:97402:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97402:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE HENRY Lord Jermyn, EARL OF St. Albans, BARON of BURY St. EDMONDS, and KNIGHT of the moſt Noble ORDER of the GARTER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Occaſion of the following Tract happening in your Country, your Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Country, between your Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men diſcourſing of Religion, and particularly the one defending that Religion wherein your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb facs="tcp:97402:3"/>is moſt eminently Principl'd; and of your exemplary Piety and Devotion therein, the eyes of your Country have been often witneſſes, hath encouraged my preſumption to this Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Nor will your Lordſhip deem the Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage of theſe few Leaves a diminution to your Glory, ſeeing you have made it the Glory of your Honourable Perſon and the Admiration and Joy of all Proteſtant Profeſſors in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that amidſt and after ſo many Tryals and Temptations in foreign parts (where you have reſided) you ſhould ſtill remain unſhaken in your Faith, that no ſelf or private Conveniences, no politick reſpects to Times or Places could al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure you from the publick profeſſion of the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> of that pure Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion confirmed to be the trueſt on Earth by the moſt ſignal proof under Heaven, even by the crim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon Stream of the dear blood of Gods Vicegerent, who for the Church ſuffered many and bitter A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonies of Life, as if the Thorns which once ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded the Temples of our Saviour, had been platted anew on the Brows of this holy Martyr.</p>
            <p>We often read of an innocent Lamb without ſpot offered in Sacrifice, but here a ſpotleſs Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd
<pb facs="tcp:97402:3"/>more innocent than his Sheep, became an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation for his Flock; a Royal Shepherd too, whoſe Holineſs entitled him to an Alliance with the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of Heaven, and made him truly a God on Earth, and Son of the Moſt High. It cannot be deny'd, but in his ſufferings for the Church, this great Patron of Religion came neer to thoſe of the Eternal Saviour of Mankind, whom the Jews put to Death for planting Religion in the World; and a People, worſe than Jews, ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd this good King for defending the ſame Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion &amp; Church which was nailed to the Croſs in Mount <hi>Calvary;</hi> his own people too imitated the Jews in perpetrating the horrid Villany, that here is a Teſtimony and Reputation to the Proteſtant Profeſſion tranſcending all the Teſtimonies of former Ages, and the greateſt that ever Age or Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion could boaſt of. In all the Romiſh Kalendar of Canonized Saints, in their whole Roll of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Martyrs, where is there one, ſince the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles time, worthy to have been a Torch bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er or born a Flambeaux at his Grave? Had <hi>Rome,</hi> for their Faith, ſuch a glorious Name to boaſt of, what Pilgrimages from their utmoſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines, what Proceſſions from all parts of their
<pb facs="tcp:97402:4"/>Territories would be made to his Shrine? Even Divine Adoration would be given at his Tomb; (and indeed ſuch Devotion would come neerer to true Worſhip there, than at all the prophane Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars they have before bowed.) And as in the Infant Plantation of Chriſts Church, the holy Shepherd (the Lord of Life) was ſmitten, and the Sheep were ſcatter'd, hid, and concealed for a ſpace; ſo likewiſe as if true Religion had not only been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, but Crucified too with this Martyr on the Scaffold, the true Church was forced to walk in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible (as to the knowledg of her Enemies) in this Land, and not to be found but in Cells and ſilent places; for then were Inſtructions to right Faith and good Life chain'd up, and temptations to Atheiſm Irreligion, and Prophaneneſs let looſe upon men: Then holy Guides and Pillars of the Church ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, ſome Death, ſome a barbarous Captivity; Perſecution raged on all her Children; then Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon triumphed, Rebellion was rampant, and with Faction and Sedition became the Epidemical Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the times; then nothing was dangerous for men to practiſe but Loyalty and Vertue, or to profeſs but the old Proteſtant Religion: Thence followed the fatal Neceſſity forevery true Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
<pb facs="tcp:97402:4"/>to be his own Prieſt, and to fortifie himſelf by conſulting the Divine Oracles and Writings, which the Saints (of old) &amp; Fathers of the Church had left to Poſterity, for our ſtrengthning againſt the Aſſaults of Schiſm. And then it was that I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed my ſelf to a ſedulous examination of thoſe Principles in Religion which Education had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill'd, and to ſearch the bottom on which my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith was founded; and it was then that I found the beſt direction for my task and purpoſe from that moſt excellent Advice (which I appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended might well ſerve every Subject as the Son of a King) of that glorified Saint (and holy Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr for the ſame Faith) left to his Son, then Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> which is able to rivet the moſt waver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Spirit on the rock of Aſſurance Indeed, who can remember his holy Life in that Faith, and his ſubmiſſion to Death for the ſame, or read his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Writings, and be faithleſs? And who can be ſo mercileſs to himſelf as not to contemplate the former and read the latter for his Confirmation in Religion, in the Religion of his King, the beſt of Kings, in the Religion proved, by undeniable Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, to be the beſt in the world.</p>
            <p>The King of Kings preſerve his Sacred Majeſty
<pb facs="tcp:97402:5"/>our Soveraign, and the Royal Progeny, and their Poſterity, in the perſeverance of the ſame profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Religion, to the perpetual honour of their Names and Crowns, the ſafety and glory of the Church and Kingdoms. And the ſame Divine Providence bleſs your Lordſhip with long and happy days, to be ſtill a Light in your Sphere by your Zeal and Conſtancy in the Proteſtant Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, to the ſtill Confuſion of Face of thoſe ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of Gods Church, whoſe malitious Impudence continually aſperſe the Devotion of great and (caſt a ſuſpicion on the Religion of) good men; and as you have fervently imitated our grand Maſter (of adored and bleſſed memory) in his tranſcendent unimitable Conſtancy in the true Faith, which ſet him (not as his Enemies machinated, in a Cloud) a Sun in full glory, ever ſhining after death, ſo your Lordſhip (after Life on Earth finiſhed) may be a Star of the next Magnitude with him in the Firmament of Glory, is the fervent Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips moſt Humble, and moſt Devoted Servant,</hi> John Underwood.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97402:5"/>
               <head>THE CHURCH-PAPIST So Called.</head>
               <p>A Church-Papiſt, or <hi>(Stilo Novo)</hi> more modernly, a Papiſt in diſguiſe, is one who holds Unity and Communion with the Church of <hi>England</hi> in a ſtrict compliance, ſubſcribes to all the Proteſtant Profeſſions of Faith, and received Principles in the ſame, yet in heart adheres (alſo) to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in all ſuch Points and Doctrines as are agreeable to Scripture, and the Apoſtolick Faith. He is known by his high Conformity to the Liturgy, Doctrine, and Diſcipline of the Church, and noted for his devout obſervance of all the Rights and Ceremonies uſed in publick Worſhip; nor can the Church impoſe the thing (not thwart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Canon of holy Scripture) to which he thinks it not his duty to incline his Obedience: He cannot be brought to countenance thoſe who would diminiſh (or ſo much as diſpute) her Authority, or la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to introduce Novelties, and ſchiſmatical Fangles into her Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, accounting ſuch as wild Boars breaking into the Vineyard to root it up, nor will he be juſtled out of his belief, of what the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el Experiment of the late Times have ſhown him, that the Lamb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skin of Reformation harbours Wolves for Deſolation. He is one who will and doth take lawful Oaths of Allegiance, Supremacy, Teſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> tendred him; and is obſtinate in nothing more than in keeping them. He peaceably ſubmits to the Government without diſhonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Reflections on Church or State, and in defence of both dares and will venture his <hi>All:</hi> He is one who eſteems Obedience better than Sacrifice, and prefers performing his Duty before his Life; He looks upon the Governours of the Church, as thoſe whom God hath ſent, and through whoſe words we are to believe in Chriſt, St. <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.20. and upon the Magiſtrate and Temporal Rulers, as Miniſters of God to us for our good, and knoweth that the Powers that be,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97402:6"/>are ordained of God, and that to reſiſt the Power is to reſiſt the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God, and will not incur Damnation by reſiſting. He is the ſame man who <hi>(ſtilo veteri)</hi> in the late Uſurpation, would not ſwallow the ſeveral unhallowed Bits (againſt Law and Honeſty) tempted on him, not the Vow and Covenant, nor ſubſcribe the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociation, publick Proteſtation, not take the League and Covenant, Abjuration (of certain Doctrines) Oaths, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> contradictory one to another, and contrary to former lawful Oaths; nor cloſe with the Engagement contrary to them all: He was the chief ſufferer in thoſe times, and ſtill is the Butt at which envenomed Arrows, from all corners, are ſhot, and principally aimed at (by the Enemies of the Church) for the firſt Deſtruction. Under the like denomination of Church-Papiſts, were then the beſt of men delivered to popular ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominy and Contempt, (preparatives for Ruine, and Fore-runners of all Confuſion) ſo expoſed were the greateſt and beſt of men, the Church or Nation of <hi>England</hi> ever produced; pretended fears and Jealouſies (of being Popiſhly addicted) aſſaulted the Throne, and pretences of Hypocriſie in Religion, made many Martyrs for the true one. The Sluce of Blood firſt opened in the beſt Counſellor of State, many Torrents followed; the Veins of Royal Majeſty it ſelf, of the great Patriarch of our Reformed Church, of the moſt Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious of the Nobility, and of many prime Chriſtians of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Profeſſion were launched, and flowing in many ſtreams made up a Red Sea.</p>
               <p>Under ſuch an Appellation and Reproach was the Author of this Paper, in the ſame uſurped Times particularly numbred and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted; and by the cruelty of the pretended Reformers ſuffered many Calamities, Plunderings, Impriſonments, Loſs of Employment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> narrowly eſcaping with life; and ſo ſtrong was the Calumny (which took away the Lives of the beſt Proteſtants in the world) caſt on the Churchmen, that it prevailed on the belief of many (who were inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent of the malicious Project) that we were Papiſts indeed, even the very Papiſts themſelves were beguiled thereby, and believed us of their perſwaſion, inſomuch that ſoon after the bleſſed Reſtauration of the Government, the Author was accoſted with their Salutes, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing their amazement, in that (now perſecution ceaſed, and a door opened for more freedom, as they ſaid (he communicated not with them in worſhip; but his refuſal of their ſolemn invitation
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97402:6"/>ſhowing them their miſtake, one of them (no mean one) ſet upon him, and made it his buſineſs to gain a Proſelyte, engaging him to comply with (or anſwer) the Arguments he ſoon after delivered in Writing, which put the Author upon a ſerious Scrutiny and Study to know his own Religion aright, and to defend it; (for he being a Layman, had then read little of Controverſie upon the Points.) He hapned at the very firſt on the beſt Lights, the Word of God, and the Word of the King, Authorities rightly underſtood and aptly applied, not to be withſtood by any in the world. The beſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection to underſtand the former, he received from the later, even from that beſt of Chriſtians and King of Proteſtants, in his ΕΙΚΩΝ ΒΑΣΙΛΙΚΗ by which were framed the following Anſwers, which have ſlept theſe many years (from their firſt Conception) and might have been dumb till the Papers had turn'd to (Aſhes, had not the now revived term of diſguiſed Papiſt been clamorous, and awakned them to face the world, that the well meaning Chriſtian may not in thought joyn with the Deceiver to reproach the Innocent, that the old Intrigue and Stratagem now on foot, may not proceed again to trapan the Nation into an Uprore and Confuſion, by firſt rendring a man criminal by aſperſion (to fit him for a deſtruction without pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) then cruelly deſtroy him for a Crime, of which he is not guilty.</p>
               <p>See here, then, ſuch a Church Papiſt diſſected, and behold him and his Religion in the following Pages.</p>
               <div n="1" type="argument">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The aforementioned Arguments of</hi> Dr. R. S. <hi>are four in number: The Firſt, from the perpetual Viſibility of the Church</hi> of Rome, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     <list type="syllogism">
                        <item>1. <hi>That Church only that is Viſible in all Ages, is the true Church;</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>But, only the Roman Church is Viſible in all Ages,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Ergo, <hi>only the Roman Church is the True Church.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Proof,</hi> THe Major is manifeſt, which I prove by St. <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.17. <hi>Dic Eccleſiae, Tell the Church:</hi> But how can we tell the Church if it be inviſible, <hi>tanquam Idea Platonica, Ergo,</hi> The Church is Viſible in all Ages.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> is clear by all Church Hiſtories, Councils, Fathers,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97402:7"/>that the Roman Church only is Viſible in all Ages, for no other Church can ſhew her Viſibility in any Kingdom, City, or Village, from the Apoſtles time to <hi>Luther, Ergo,</hi> only the Roman Church is the True Church.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="argument">
                  <head>The Second Argument from Succeſſion, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     <list type="syllogism">
                        <item>2. <hi>That Church only that hath lawful Succeſſion, is the True Church;</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>But, only the Roman Church hath lawful Succeſſion,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Ergo, <hi>only the Roman Church is the True Church.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Proof,</hi> THe <hi>Major</hi> is proved by St. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> That Church (ſaith he) in which is Succeſſion, is the Rock againſt which Hell-Gates cannot prevail. And <hi>Irenaeus</hi> ſaith, <hi>Succeſſione con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fundimus: omnes,</hi> Succeſſion confound all Hereticks; but only the Roman Church have lawful Succeſſion; <hi>Numerate Sacerdotes vel ab ipſa</hi> Petri <hi>ſede, &amp; in illo ordine Patrum quis cui ſucceſſit videte,</hi> as, ſaith St. <hi>Auguſt. In hoc ordine ſucceſſionis nullus Donatiſta Epiſcopus inveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur:</hi> And our Engliſh Biſhops had no ſucceſſion from Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, for immediately after their Conſecration, <hi>Stapleton, Harding, &amp;c.</hi> told them to their faces they were no Biſhops; <hi>Ergo,</hi> only the Roman Church have lawful Succeſſion.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="argument">
                  <head>The Third Argument from pretended peculiar Privileges belonging to the Roman Church, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     <list type="syllogism">
                        <item>3. <hi>That Church only that have confuted, and anathematiz'd all Hereticks, converted Nations, deprived Schiſmatical Biſhops, reſtored Orthodox Biſhops, called Councils,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that is the True Church.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>But only the Roman is ſuch,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Ergo, <hi>only the Roman is the True Church.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Proof,</hi> THe <hi>Major</hi> is plain, becauſe theſe Privileges belong to the Authority of the Mother Church, which is <hi>Matrix &amp; Radix omnium Eccleſiarum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:97402:7"/>
                  <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> is proved, for, <hi>In Eccleſia Romana ſemper viguit Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicae Cathedrae Principatus;</hi> therefore in the Oriental Councils, when ſome Biſhops would not agree, divers cryed out <hi>Romam am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulent, Let them go to</hi> Rome: <hi>Nam a</hi> Petro (<hi>inquit</hi> Auguſt.) <hi>ipſe E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopatus &amp; tota Authoritas nominis hujus emerſit,</hi> and 'tis manifeſt no Proteſtant Church ever confuted Hereticks, converted Nations, deprived Schiſmaticks, reſtored Orthodox Biſhops, but ſlept <hi>Endi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mion</hi>'s Sleep for above a thouſand years, or like a Didopper dived in the Apoſtles time, and never roſe again until <hi>Squire Luther,</hi> that ſecond <hi>Elias,</hi> that fift <hi>Evangeliſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="argument">
                  <head>The Fourth Argument, from Univerſality of the Roman Church, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     <list type="syllogism">
                        <item>4. <hi>That Church is only Catholick, which is diſperſed through all Nations.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>But only the Roman is diſperſed through all Nations,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Ergo, <hi>the Roman Church only is the Catholick Church.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Proof,</hi> THe <hi>Major</hi> is proved, for Univerſality is an evident mark of the Catholick Church: <hi>Si veſtra Eccleſia</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Auguſt.) ſit Catholica, oſtendite per univerſam terram ramos ſuos copia ubertatis extendere;</hi> for no Hereſie can be Univerſal, no Heretick can be Catholick, Proteſtants are ſo far from Univerſality, that 'tis as hard a matter to find a Proteſtant in fifteen hundred, as <hi>motum in vacuo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> is as evident, that the Roman Church was diſperſed through all Nations, by St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the Romans, 3.8. where he faith, that the Roman Faith was Preached in all the World, that is <hi>Peter</hi>'s Faith; and what Faith the Romans had then, the very ſame they have at this preſent; for the Roman Church is not to be new bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom'd, neither to be reformed of new Calciners: <hi>Fidei enim Regula una omnino eſt, ſola, immobilis, irreformabilis</hi> (as <hi>Tertullian</hi>) the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Faith once delivered to the Apoſtles by the prime verity, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and aſſiſted by the Holy Ghoſt for ever, cannot be alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the Church being built upon a Rock, need no repairing of new Maſons: <hi>Soliditas illius</hi> Petrae, <hi>quae Apoſtolorum Principe eſt lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>data,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97402:8"/>perpetua eſt: &amp; ſicut</hi> Petra <hi>permanet quod in Chriſto</hi> Petrus <hi>credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit ita permanet quod</hi> PetrO Chriſtus <hi>inſtituit.</hi> Here St. <hi>Leo</hi> ſaith, the Church is Perpetual, and cannot fail ſo long as Chriſt is the Son of the Living God: And although the Proteſtant Church be fallible, yet the Roman is infallible; therefore, <hi>Vivat Fides Catholica, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat Eccleſia Romana; quae fuit tempore Apoſtolorum, &amp; eſt eritque per ſecula ſempiterna.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <div n="1" type="argument">
                  <head>THE ANSWER.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I Derive not my Faith from <hi>Luther</hi> or <hi>Calvin,</hi> as Beginners of it, yet do confeſs with St. <hi>Paul, (Acts</hi> 24.14.) that aften the way which they call Hereſie, ſo worſhip I the Lord God of my Fathers; I mean, as thoſe Fathers did, whom <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> calls <hi>Patres Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trûm,</hi> profeſſing the Ancient Catholick Faith; all the Articles of my Faith being grounded on Scripture, and the conſtant belief of Fathers and Couneils in the Church of Chriſt the firſt four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Antiqua Eccleſia primisquingentis Aunis vera Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clsſia fuit.</hi> Bell. lib. 4. de not. Eccl. c. 9.</note> The Opinions of any Poſterior Fathers, where they vary from the Doctrine of the Firſt, I think it unſafe to follow. For St. <hi>Hierom</hi> teacheth me well; <hi>Nec Parentum nec majorum Error ſequendus eſt; ſed Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritas Scripturarum &amp; Dei docentis imperium; nam</hi> Judaei <hi>poſt</hi> Baalim <hi>abierunt quos didicerunt a Patribus</hi> (In Jerem. ca. 9.) We are not to take error by Tradition from our Fathers or Anceſtors, but the true ſence of holy Scriptures is to be followed, and the Power of God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing us in them, for the Jews went after <hi>Baal</hi> by the example of their Fathers: <hi>As your Fathers did, ſo do ye: Acts</hi> 7.51. I am of the Apoſtles belief, and I am ſure they were no Papiſts; rather Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, proteſting the Truth and ſincerity of Faith againſt Error and Schiſm: So we by receiving the true Sacraments (which are called <hi>Viſible Signs proteſting the Faith</hi>) proteſt againſt thoſe which are corrupted, and againſt all Doctrines contrary to Scripture and the Apoſtolick Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſo in that ſence you may call me Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant. Now to prove only the Roman Church to be the True Church, you ſay: <hi>That Church only that is Viſible in all Ages is the True Church; but only the Roman Church is Viſible in all Ages,</hi> Ergo,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97402:8"/>
                     <hi>only the Roman Church is the True Church.</hi> And to prove the <hi>Major,</hi> you inſtance the words of St. <hi>Mathew, Dic Eccleſiae</hi> To which I anſwer, that 'tis not ſaid <hi>Dic Romanae Eccleſiae, (Tell it to the Roman Church)</hi> therefore makes no more for <hi>Rome</hi> than for <hi>Greece,</hi> or any other place where the Church is, hath been, or ſhall be. And to prove the <hi>Minor,</hi> you only ſay 'tis cleer by Church Hiſtories, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, and Fathers, that the Roman Church only is Viſible, but bring not one particular proof from any of them to make it evident, and evince that the Church was no where elſe Viſible; for Hiſtory alſo tells us that the Eaſt or Greek Church, though often in great miſery and perſecution, was, and is a Church from the Apoſtles time: So that Argument which is common to others, you cannot appropriate only to the Roman; ſeeing it makes as much for the Greek Church (in whoſe Language the Oracles of the Son of Ged were written) as for it: The Greek Church was firſt honoured with the Original writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Goſpel, and the Latin Church had it only by Franſlation from it.</p>
                  <p>That there was and is a Church conſtant in all Ages (though not apparently flouriſhing, and viſible at all times to all the world) I not deny; but that there is no Church where 'tis not Splendid and Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to all eyes, you have not yet made any ways apparent: Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Ark of God was not leſs an Ark, in being in <hi>Dagon</hi>'s Tent and the Hands of the Philiſtines. Perſecution (the fare of the Church Militant) obſcured the Churches Rays in many Nations, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſo totally Eclipſed her, as ſhe was not viſible to Humane Eyes: Beſides, your Poſition, that Viſibility is the only mark of the true Church, you have not proved to be granted be Churches differing from the Roman, therefore is a Principle of your own, and a beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the Queſtion. I deny it to be the only mark, for a mark muſt be infallible, and
<list type="syllogism">
                        <item>
                           <hi>That mark which may poſſibly deceive, and is common both to a True and a Falſe Church, and may as probably lead to the one as the other; is no certain infallible mark to find the true Church.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>But Viſibility may deceive, being common to both; and may as readily lead to a Falſe as a True Church.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Therefore Viſibility no ſure mark and unerring Rule to find the True Church.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Major</hi> is undeniable, bearing its own Proof, Truth, and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97402:9"/>in it ſelf. The <hi>Minor</hi> is apparent in all Ages, even from the beginning of the World to this day: Go up into Paradiſe, the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of <hi>Eden,</hi> there was Truth and Falſhood, even as ſoon as God had laid his Church, the Devil began to build a Chappel; for (in <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis</hi>) not long after, <hi>Et Deus dixit (And God ſaid, &amp;c.)</hi> the Devil was buſie to ſet up a falſe Worſhip and wrong Obedience; and then comes, <hi>Et Serpens dixit, And the Serpent ſaid,</hi> which viſibly and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably deceived our firſt Parents. The Church was with <hi>Moſes</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> there were Magicians and mock Miracles; Falſhood ever followed the Truth, or Truth found it where it went: There were Calves in <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> there were worſhipers of <hi>Baal;</hi> Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror is almoſt as old in the world as Truth: No ſooner went the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles out to Preach, but a falſe Doctrine appeared in <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> and his Followers, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.14. In one place or other Erroneous and falſe Churches have been always Viſible to this day, (even when the true Church have been obſcured by Perſecutions) for ſo it muſt be according to the ſaying of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.19. <hi>Oportet eſſe Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes;</hi> Were the idolatrous People in the time of <hi>Elias, Achas, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes,</hi> and others, the True Church, becauſe they only were Viſible to the World? For where was Viſibility of the True Church, when the Prophet cried out and complained (1 <hi>Kings) He only was left a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone?</hi> (ſo a true Church may be, though not viſible, for there were ſeven thouſand true Worſhippers which he knew not of.) Where was Viſibility when the Shepherd was ſmitten, and the Sheep ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, hid, and concealed? <hi>Zach.</hi> 13.7. <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.32. Where was Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of the True Church in the time of <hi>Diocleſian</hi> the Emperour, when neither Church, Book, nor Men eſcaped? Was ſhe not as St. <hi>Joh.</hi> teſtifieth, <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.6. fled into a Deſart where ſhe ſhould not be found for a ſpace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> (in Math. 24.) ſaith, In the time of Abomination of Deſolation, (<hi>viz.</hi> of wicked Hereſie,) <hi>Nulla probatio poteſt Chriſtianitatis, &amp;c.</hi> No proof of Chriſtianity can be made, or refuge found for Chriſtians to know the true Faith, but only the Divine Scripture: So the Church of Antichriſt may be Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible and Flouriſhing, when the true Church of Chriſt is in obſcuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and hath no Luſtre. Therefore Viſibility is not in all Ages and all times an infallible mark of the true Church, but is a mark alſo of a falſe one; and ſo a true Church hath been, and may be, though not Viſible to Humane Eyes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Your next Poſition is from Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="argument">
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:97402:9"/>
                  <list type="syllogism">
                     <item>2. <hi>That Church that have lawfull Succeſſion is the True Church;</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>But only the Roman have lawful Succeſſion,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Ergo, <hi>only the Roman Church is the True Church.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>To prove the <hi>Major</hi> you twice inſtance St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> but direct to no place where; therefore I know not whether he ſpeaks as you repreſent him; or if he doth, whether he denotes a Succeſſion in Place, of Perſons, or of Doctrine; and you bring in <hi>Irenaeus</hi> to ſay, <hi>Succeſſione Confundimus omnes,</hi> &amp;c. but there is no ſuch ſaying in the manner you mention, found in <hi>Irenaeus;</hi> 'tis only corruptly quoted by <hi>Bellarmine, (Bellar. li.</hi> 4. <hi>de notis Eccleſ. ca.</hi> 8. <hi>Sect.</hi> 2.) nor have I heard or found <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> or any other Father make Local, Perſonal, Viſible, and Continued Succeſſion, a neceſſary Sign or Mark of the True Church in any one place, (as though a True Church could not be in any place without it,) yet the Faith was delivered over by Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion in ſome places or other to their time, and is to our time, and ſhall be till there be no time; for a True Church may be, hath been, and is in places, where there hath not been Continued, Viſible, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Succeſſion. Were not <hi>Jeruſalem, Antioch, &amp;c.</hi> and others in the Primitive times true Churches, yet Succeſſion of Biſhops hath not continually ſucceeded in them to this day, and later Churches are true likewiſe: <hi>Conſtat omnem Doctrinam quae cum illis Eccleſiis A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolicis Matricibus Originalibus Fidei conſpiret Veritati deputandam:</hi> So ſaith <hi>Tertullian, De praeſcript. adverſ. Haeret. c.</hi> 21. And in the ſame place, <hi>Eccleſiae poſteriores non minus Apoſtolicae deputantur pro conſanguinitate Doctrinae:</hi> The Succeſſion <hi>Irenaeus</hi> ſtood upon, was of the Churches then in <hi>Aſia,</hi> and of <hi>Smyrna,</hi> where <hi>Polycarpus</hi> ſat Biſhop, as that of <hi>Rome. Teſtimonium his perhibent quae ſunt in</hi> Aſia <hi>Eccleſiae omnes, &amp; qui uſque adhuc ſucceſſerunt</hi> Polycarpo, Iren. l. 3. <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſ.</hi> Haeret. ca. 3. And St. <hi>Hierom</hi> tells us, <hi>Eccleſia non in parietibus conſiſtit,</hi> (in Pſal. 133.) So Succeſſion in the Fathers Account is not tyed to Place, or Perſon, but to the verity of Doctrine; as <hi>Tertullian (de praeſcript. c.</hi> 32.) <hi>Ad hanc formam provocabantur ab illis Eccleſiis, quae licet nullum ex Apoſtolis, vel Apoſtolicis Authorem ſuum proferunt, ut multo poſteriores, quae denique quotidie inſtituuntur, tamen in eadem fide conſpirantes; non minus Apoſtolicae deputantur pro canſanguinitate Doctrinae;</hi> ſhewing that modern Churches, ſuch as are daily inſtituted and ſet up agreeing and linking together in the ſame true Faith, are
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97402:10"/>no leſs to be eſteemed Apoſtolical for their neerneſs and conſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Doctrine; and to that we have as good Succeſſion as any Chriſtian Church this day in the whole Catholick Body, the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on profeſſed in the Church of <hi>England</hi> being neareſt of any Church now in being, to the Primitive Chriſtian Church. Churches that have Doctrine, that is not allied in Blood, to that of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, have no lawful or good Succeſſion; for <hi>Conſanguinitas Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinae</hi> is required: <hi>Irenaeus</hi> ſpeaks plain, <hi>Illis Preſbyteris obediendum eſt, qui cum Epiſcopatus Succeſſione Chariſſima acceperunt veritatis.</hi> Iren. l. 4. ca. 43. We are to obey thoſe Prieſts, who with their Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in the Office of Biſhop have received the Pledge or Gift of Truth: whereupon <hi>Stapleton (Relic. cont.</hi> 1. <hi>q.</hi> 4. <hi>A.</hi> 2. <hi>Notab.</hi> 1.) is forced to confeſs, <hi>ſucceſſio nec locorum tantum eſt neo perſonarum, ſed etiam verae &amp; ſanae Doctrinae.</hi> And why it cannot be of Paſtours he again tells us (<hi>Notab.</hi> 4. <hi>ibid.) name Paſtore Lups fleri poteſt;</hi> which is true, many great men have turned Hereticks; <hi>Judas</hi> chang'd from an Apoſtle to a Devil, ſo 'tis the eaſie for others to change from Shepherds into Wolves. Nor can the <hi>Roman</hi> Prelates pretend they have only this <hi>veràm et ſanam Doctrinam,</hi> or claim a lawful ſucceſſion of Paſtors continually holding entire the Unity and the Eaith, for they have not kept the Unity of the Church, but have had more Schiſms among them than any other Church, above thirty acknowledged by their own Chronologer <hi>Onuphrius;</hi> Even Popes themſelves have many of them (by confeſſion of ſeveral Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Authors who have written of their Lives) been very vile, er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous, Heretical, &amp;c. So 'tis clear <hi>Rome</hi> hath no lawful Succeſſion, by confeſſion; they have only a Succeſſion of groſs Superſtitions and Errors for a bout a thouſand years, for which they can ſhew no Practice on Warrant from the Apoſtles. You further ſay, That our Engliſh Biſhops had no Succeſſion from Roman Catholick, for immediately after Conſcoration, <hi>Stapleton, Harding, &amp;c.</hi> (your own men) told them to their faces they were no Biſhops, <hi>Ergo,</hi> only the Roman Church have lawful Succeſſion.</p>
                  <p>I ſee you are put to hard ſtraits for proof, that, ſeeing the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers will not ſpeak for you, you are forced to be your own Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, which with me is leſs than nothing (for who will or can take an Adverſary's bare objections for a ſufficient confutation of a matter in queſtion) for by this your Argument and Rule of proof,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97402:10"/>ſhould I tell you that any of our Party ſay <hi>Stapleton, Harding,</hi> &amp;c. were no Scholars (though indeed they were great Clarks) and ſhould I ſay they were damnable Hereticks and forſakers of the Truth (as in truth they are) you ought to admit it as a convincing Teſtimony (elſe why do you obtrude your ſayings for proof?) but let that paſs. You confeſs Engliſh Biſhops had Conſecration from the Roman, and ſo enabled and qualified for the ſervice of the Church; If then the Roman had any lawful power to conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate (which I deny not) I do not queſtion but their Conſecration is valid enough and hold good, notwithſtanding <hi>Stapleton</hi> and <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings</hi> words to the contrary; for ſuch ſayings do not unordain, and ſo we have your Succeſſion and Conſecration to boot. But whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ordinary Miſſion or Ordination be ſo abſolutely neceſſary to the being of Truth, as though Truth could nor be without it, is with me a queſtion, ſeeing Chriſt encouraged the Faithful that did wonders in Chriſt's name and was not ſent, (St. <hi>Mark</hi> 9.39, 40.) forbid him not he is on our part, &amp;c. nor did I ever conceive a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity lay on the Engliſh Church to receive Orders from <hi>Rome,</hi> more than on the Roman to receive Orders from it, ſeeing we were a Church Apoſtolick aſſoon, yea were a Church before any ſettlement of a Church in <hi>Rome.</hi> The Religion of Chriſt was received <hi>in Brittain, tempore (ut ſcimus) ſummo Tiberii Caeſaris,</hi> in the latter time of <hi>Tiberius Caeſar,</hi> as ſaith St. <hi>Gildas (de excid. Brit.)</hi> the ſame is acknowledged by your own man <hi>Baronius;</hi> whereas St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> kept in Jury long after <hi>Tiberius</hi> his death: And (as <hi>Theodoret</hi> and <hi>Sophronimus</hi> Patriarchs of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> affirm) the Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> firſt taught in <hi>Britain;</hi> Alſo <hi>Ariſtobulus</hi> mentioned <hi>Romans</hi> 16. came to this Iſle and diſcharged the Office of a Biſhop, as <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rotheus</hi> witneſſeth, and in his <hi>Synopſis</hi> alſo averreth <hi>Simon Zelotes Chriſtum praedicavit in</hi> Britannia <hi>ubi crucifixus occiſus et ſepultus eſt;</hi> The ſame alſo affirmeth <hi>Nicephorus lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 40.) <hi>Simon Zelotes Evangelii Doctrinam ad occidentalem Oceanum Inſulaſque Britannicas perfert.</hi> And <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea An. Dom.</hi> 53. taught the Goſpel in <hi>Britain</hi> as <hi>Baleus Flemingus</hi> and others affirm, likewiſe <hi>Tertullian</hi> who lived <hi>An. Chriſti</hi> 200, ſaith, <hi>Britanorum loca Romanis inapoeſſa Chriſto ſubdita ſunt</hi> (<hi>adverſ. Judaeos cap.</hi> 7.8;) After him <hi>Origin An. Chriſti</hi> 260. witneſſeth <hi>Britanniam in Chriſtianam conſentire Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem.</hi> So it is evident and moſt clear that Apoſtles and Apoſtolick
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97402:11"/>men delivered over the Faith to us, and were the firſt Planters; we had many Waterers after of this Plantation, and a ſucceſſion of Doctrine by confeſſion on all ſides. St. <hi>Jerom</hi> alſo <hi>Anno</hi> 405. records <hi>Gallia, Britanniá, Africa,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>unum Chriſtum adorant, u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam obſervant Regulam veritatis:</hi> In which time <hi>Bellarmine</hi> confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the Church was a true Apoſtolick Church, <hi>Antiqua Eccleſia primis quingentis Annis vera Eccleſia fuit,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>(Bel. l.</hi> 4. <hi>de notab. Eccl. cap.</hi> 9.) and then, <hi>viz.</hi> the firſt four hundred years we and <hi>Rome</hi> were of one joint Belief and Faith from one Fountain (Chriſt <hi>Jeſus</hi> and his Apoſtles) and the ſame faith we had then, the ſame we have now, we hold to the old Foundation, the Scripture, Creed, and, ractice of the general Church in thoſe times; ſo are we a true Church and a right Member of the Catholick, having lawful ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of Doctrine, convey'd to us (as before is proved) from A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and Apoſtolick men; whereby it's evident we are no Nove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts nor any of our Profeſſion, the Antiquity whereof our very Enemies do acknowledge.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reinerus</hi> a Roman Inquiſitor (above three hundred years ſince) ſpeaking of the Profeſſors at <hi>Lyons,</hi> calling them <hi>Valdenſae, Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtae, &amp;c.</hi> in contempt, ſaith, they are more pernitious to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> than all other Sects for three cauſes; Firſt, being of lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger continuance than any other, the Sect enduring ever ſince the Apoſtles. Secondly, It is general, creeping into all Lands. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, It hath a great ſhew of Godlineſs, they live juſtly, believe all things well concerning God, and all the Articles contained in the Creed, only they Blaſpheme in hating the Church of <hi>Rome, &amp;c.</hi> He calls us indeed a Sect, as of old, the Prieſts of the Jews called the Church of Chriſtians, a Sect of <hi>Nazarites, Acts,</hi> 24.5. but you ſee, by Confeſſion we had our Doctrine in former Ages, and were a Church from the Beginning, and are not eſtranged from the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> where ſhe holds the Truth, but ſhe from us and the true Catholick Church of Chriſt; nor do we depart from her (as they charge us) or are any further remote from her, than ſhe her ſelf is from her primitive Purity, antient Principles, from Scripture, Reaſon, Charity, Antiouity, and from what ſhe was in her beſt of times: our preſent Church of <hi>England</hi> (though of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten have been under clouds and heavy perſecutions) ſtill retaining the primitive verity to this day. So your ſecond Argument is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valid
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97402:11"/>in that you have not proved (nor can prove) that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath this lawful Succeſſion of uncorrupted Doctrine and Principles, or that ſucceſſion of Paſtors is neceſſarily tied to one particular place for ever to make the being of the Catholick Church, as though the univerſal Church of Chriſt could ceaſe to be, if <hi>Rome</hi> and her Prelates were extinct and turn'd to Aſhes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="argument">
                  <head>Your third Argument from pretended Privileges belonging to the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     <list type="syllogism">
                        <item>3. <hi>That Church only that have confuted and anathematized all Hereticks, converted Nations, deprived and reſtored Biſhops, called Councils,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that is, the true Church.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>But only the</hi> Roman <hi>is ſuch;</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Ergo, <hi>only the</hi> Roman <hi>is the true Church.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </head>
                  <p>The Major (you ſay) is plain, becauſe theſe Privileges belong to the Authority of the Mother-Church, which is, <hi>Matrix &amp; Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dix omnium Eccleſiarum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwer, you ſhould firſt have proved her to be the Mother-Church <hi>&amp; Radix, &amp;c.</hi> before you exerciſe (or can claim) the Authority of a Mother; I would fain know what Church is the Mother of the Roman; or is <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf Motherleſs; for I deny her to be the Mother of the univerſal Church of God: yet do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree that thoſe Privileges (you mention) do belong to the Authority of the Catholick Church; but 'tis an inſolent and intolerable uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation (of the Rights and Privileges of the Univerſal Church) for any particular Church to confine all the Catholick Privileges to her particular ſelf, I am ſure ſhe hath not this power from Chriſt to judge and condemn her Siſters; for ſhe is not <hi>Matrix &amp; Radix omnium Eccleſiarum</hi> (as you ſay) there were elder than ſhe (there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe at beſt but a Daughter Church, and Siſter to others) <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> (if any particular) was it, as was propheſied of old, <hi>Mic.</hi> 4.2. and fulfilled, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.47. and ſo <hi>Theodoret, lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Hiſt. Eccl. cap.</hi> 9.) tells us, <hi>Eccleſia Hieroſolymitana quae aliarum omnium Mater:</hi> And Men were firſt called Chriſtians (not at <hi>Rome</hi> but) at <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch, Acts.</hi> 11.26. St. <hi>Gregory Nazian.</hi> ſaith, The Church of <hi>Caeſaria</hi> was <hi>Mater prope omnium Eccleſiarum,</hi> meaning of neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97402:12"/> Churches, not of the whole Catholick Church: <hi>Et Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantinopolitana Eccleſia dicitur omnium aliarum caput;</hi> ſo in that ſenſe, and no other, <hi>Rome</hi> may be called Head of thoſe Churches in her Patriarchat. Every particular Church that teacheth the Catholick Doctrine may be called Catholick, (as a Member of the univerſal) and ſo was the particular Roman whilſt it held all things true concerning the Faith; but never was ſhe <hi>Mater &amp; Radix om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium Eccleſiarum,</hi> for the Univerſal Church hath no particular or locall Root of its being, <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as I ſaid before, if any, was it. Or if you will have a particular Root of the Catholick Church, 'tis in the Eaſt, not in the Weſt at <hi>Rome—ſe praeciſam eſſe a Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice orientalium Eccleſiurum, &amp;c.</hi> St. <hi>Auguſt. Epiſt.</hi> 170, But the Head, Root, Matrix, Fountaine, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> and all other particular Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, is the Catholick Church and her Unity, and to break her Uunity by uſurping a Power or Priority, which Chriſt never gave, is at the leaſt abominable, if not certainly damnable; 'tis againſt a command too, The Text is clear, <hi>There was a ſtrife among the Apoſtles which ſhould be greateſt, St. Luke,</hi> 22.14. Chriſt anſwered them, <hi>The Princes and Rulers exerciſe Dominion,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>but it ſhall not be ſo with you; He that will be greateſt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>St, Matt.</hi> 20.26. There is no Priority much leſs Superiority given to Churches National; <hi>Tertullian</hi> tells us, <hi>Omnes Primae, &amp; omnes Apoſtolicae, dum unam omnes probant unita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem (de praeſcript. adverſ. Haeret. cap.</hi> 20.) <hi>Porro unam eſſe primam Apoſtolicam ex qua reliquae hanc nulli loco affigit</hi> B. Rhenanus: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not at <hi>Rome.</hi> And it is to be obſerved, that <hi>Tertullian,</hi> long ſince, numbering the then Apoſtolical Churches reckons <hi>Rome</hi> laſt of them, (<hi>Tertull. ibid. cap.</hi> 32.) and <hi>Pamelius</hi> lately puts <hi>Rome</hi> after others (<hi>cap.</hi> 21. <hi>num.</hi> 129.) what you ſpeak out of St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin, In Eccleſia Romana ſemper viguit Apoſtolicae Cathedrae Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipatus,</hi> that in <hi>Rome</hi> there did always flouriſh the Principality of an Apoſtolick Chair (in relation to the Weſt and South parts of the Church, all the other four Apoſtolical Chairs being in the Eaſt) doth not give <hi>Rome,</hi> nor the Pope thereof, power to exerciſe this Principality (beyond his Limits, out of his own Patriarchate) o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the whole Church of Chriſt: for in the ſame Epiſtle of St. <hi>Auguſt. (Epiſt.</hi> 162.) <hi>Melciades</hi> then Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> had leave granted him to hear a matter of the Donatiſts adjudged by the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frican</hi> Biſhops, and other Biſhops by the Emperour were ſent Judges
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97402:12"/>to determine with him, for if he had done it without leave the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle tells us it had been an uſurpation, ſeeing <hi>(ad cujus curam, &amp;c. ibid.)</hi> it belonged to the Emperours care and charge, and that he is to give an account to God for it. Yea a Pope himſelf ſaith 'tis Antichriſtian to be ſtiled univerſal Biſhop, St. <hi>Greg. l.</hi> 4. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 78 monſtrous and blaſphemous, <hi>Abſit a cordibus Chriſtianorum Nomen illud Blaſphemiae, ibid. Epiſt.</hi> 76: and further, (St. <hi>Greg. Epiſt.</hi> 83.) <hi>In iſto ſceleſto vocabulo conſentire nihil aliud eſt quam fidem perdere.</hi> So the Roman was not then univerſal Biſhop, had no power over Patriarchs and National Biſhops, no Monarch over the whole mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litant Church for near ſix hundred years after Chriſt: and <hi>Britain</hi> in thoſe times was never ſubject to the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> for it had a Primate of its own (<hi>Et a Patriarcha non datur Appellatio,</hi> ſaith the Civil Law) from whom lies no Appeal. Now then the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral power of anathematizing Hereticks, depriving Schiſmaticks, reſtoring Orthodox Biſhops, <hi>&amp;c,</hi> belong to the Catholick Church Militant, and her Authority in general Councils lawfully by her called and conſtituted; and that the Catholick Church is our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther no man will deny that accounts God to be his Father. But this Holy Catholick Church (mentioned in the Apoſtle's Creed) is not the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> nor any other particular Church on Earth: The Holy Catholick Church there ſpoken of contains not only the whole militant Church on Earth but the whole Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant alive in Heaven; for ſo St. <hi>Auguſt. Euch. cap.</hi> 56. <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia hic tota accipienda eſt, non ſolum ex parte quae peregrinatur in terris, &amp;c. verùm etiam ex illa quae in Caelis:</hi> And who converted Nations originally? Did not Chriſt ſend out his Apoſtles, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty Diſciples at another time, and then after ſent many more? were not then Apoſtles Apoſtolick men, and the general Church they that converted and confuted Nations and planted the Church of Chriſt in the World? Now this Holy Catholick Church, before ever <hi>Rome</hi> was a Church, is <hi>Matrix &amp; Radix omnium Eccleſiarum,</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> as well as other. The Catholick Church was ever one and the ſame Church, (<hi>viz.</hi> the Church of God ſpread over the whole World (and as before deſcribed by St. <hi>Auguſt.) Rome</hi> could never be it, for if <hi>Rome,</hi> a particular Church, can be now the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, then by the ſame Rule (if it be not out of Rule) ſome other particular Church, before it, was the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97402:13"/>Church; and how came that to loſe it and <hi>Rome</hi> to get it, that it is now, as you ſay, tranſlated to <hi>Rome;</hi> and doth it not follow by the ſame rule that <hi>Rome</hi> (alſo) may <hi>tranſire in non Eccleſiam, paſs way in no Church;</hi> for what Patent or holy Charter from Heaven hath <hi>Rome</hi> above the former, and above other particular Churches that it ſhall there remain to the end of the World? Nay, they that moſt ſtand for it, even the greateſt Champion <hi>Rome</hi> hath, can only ſay, <hi>'Tis a pious and probable Opinion to think, Cathedram Petri non poſſe ſeperari a Roma &amp; proinde Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam Eccleſiam non poſſe errare vel deficere. (Bellar. de Ro. Pont. cap.</hi> 4.) ſo 'tis but pretended probality, and that is no proof able to convince: However, he that thinks the contrary, <hi>viz.</hi> that the particular Church of <hi>Rome</hi> can err and fall away from the Faith (which the true Church can never do, I mean the Catholick Church before deſcribed can never fall away from the Faith) and St. <hi>Peters</hi> Chair be ſevered from <hi>Rome,</hi> is by <hi>Bellarmines</hi> own confeſſion no Heretick, for he adds, <hi>Contraria ſententia nec eſt Haeretica nec ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſta erronia (Bellarm. ibid.)</hi> And if the Apoſtolick Chair can be removed from <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Roman Church fall away from the Faith, then it is ſo far <hi>being the only Catholick,</hi> that it ceaſeth to be a part of the Catholick Church; where it appeareth that <hi>Rome</hi> never was, is, or can be, <hi>The only Catholick Church of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="argument">
                  <head>Your fourth Argument, from Univerſality of the Roman Church, hath its Anſwer already in a great meaſure: But ſomething more I ſhall particularly anſwer to the ſame, which you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound, thus.
<list type="syllogism">
                        <item>
                           <hi>Arg.</hi> 4. <hi>That Church is only Catholick which is diſperſed through all Nations.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>But only the Roman is diſperſed through all Nations,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Ergo <hi>the Roman only is the Catholick Church.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </head>
                  <p>And how comes the denomination of the Church to be changed from Chriſtian to Roman; certainly 'tis no ſmall fellony to rob the Church of the more honourable Appellation and give it your own name. Men were firſt called Chriſtians at <hi>Antioch;</hi> and yet the Univerſal Church was never ſtiled <hi>Antiochian.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:97402:13"/>
                  <p>If you make a difference between the Chriſtian Faith and the Roman, ſpeak out and confeſs it; If you mean the Chriſtian Faith, why do you not ſay ſo? alter your Minor Propoſition and the concluſion will follow for the Church of Chriſt, and I'le aſſent to it without more ado, for then your Propoſition will be true and you will contend without an Adverſary. But have you any other Doctrine can parallel this Sacriledge in taking away the Chriſtian Name from the univerſal Church of Chriſt? As though the Spouſe of Chriſt could become Anabaptiſt, forget her Virgin Name and change her Beloved. Is Chriſt and <hi>Rome</hi> convertible? Is the Goſpel of Chriſt become the Goſpel of the Pope? or hath the Pope a Goſpel of his own that is ſpread over the World? was there not a true Church (that had <hi>Radix Eſſentiae,</hi> and is the Root, Eſſence and Being to <hi>Rome</hi> and other particular Churches) before <hi>Rome</hi> received the Faith? And what was that Church called? not Roman ſurely: And why did you not ſay the Church of <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> or the Church of <hi>Antioch, &amp;c.</hi> (where the firſt Plantation was) is diſperſed through all Nations; <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Church of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, Antioch, &amp;c.</hi> only is the Catholick Church? it had been more tollerable though as little to ſence. The firſt Appellation (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ever <hi>Rome</hi> was a Church) <hi>viz.</hi> Chriſtian, ſhall ſtand with me for ever: I dare not change from Chriſtian to Roman, in as much as Chriſtian Religion is elder and was before ever <hi>Rome</hi> was converted; therefore Chriſtian, not Roman, is the primitive and right term and name of the univerſal Church. Beſides, How the Roman (or any particular Church) can be the Catholick (for at beſt ſhe was but a Catholick) Church, is no ways apparent. St. <hi>Cyril</hi> tells us, <hi>Catholica eſt illa quae diffuſa eſt per univerſum Orbem; Rome</hi> is not the univerſal (but the Chriſtian Church is) ſo not Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick in extent. <hi>Romana Eccleſia particularis</hi> confeſſeth <hi>Bellarmin, (lib.</hi> 4. <hi>de R. Pont. c.</hi> 4.) ſo not the Catholick Church; <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf muſt be judged by Scripture and the Catholick Church (and is right no further than it agrees with the Catholick) and not the Catholick Church by it. Our fierce Adverſary <hi>Stapleton,</hi> pours out his Reaſon why Roman is eſteemed Catholick, <hi>Quia ejus Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munio erat evidenter &amp; certiſſimè cum tota Catholica;</hi> So you ſee the Communion of the Roman was with the Catholick, not of the Catholick with it: And St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> in the rent and open Schiſm
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97402:14"/>between <hi>Cornelius</hi> and <hi>Novatian</hi> employed his Legates, <hi>&amp;c. Elabora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent ut ad Catholicae Eccleſiae unitatem ſciſſi sorpor is membra componerent:</hi> Now the members of this torn Body were they of <hi>Rome,</hi> then in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen Schiſm between <hi>Cornelius</hi> and <hi>Novatian, (St. Cypr. li.</hi> 2. <hi>Ep.</hi> 10.) And St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> endeavoured to bring <hi>Rome</hi> to the Unity of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick; ſo <hi>Rome</hi> then was not <hi>The Catholick,</hi> nor is the <hi>Radix, &amp;c.</hi> or can ſhe be her own Original. There is a double Root, (as one learnedly obſerves) <hi>Radix Eſſentiae,</hi> which gives <hi>Eſſence</hi> and <hi>Being</hi> to <hi>Rome</hi> and all other particular Churches, and there is <hi>Radix Exiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae,</hi> as <hi>Rome</hi> with all other particular Churches (and no more than other Patriarchal Churches) which was and is the Root of the Churches Exiſtence, agreeable to that known and received Rule in Art, that <hi>Univerſals give Eſſence to their Particulars, and Particulars ſupply their Univerſals with Exiſtence.</hi> But to ſhut up and confine the Univerſal Church of Chriſt, (as it is now ſpread) in the narrow com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs of <hi>Rome</hi> only, is ridiculous Nonſence. <hi>Eccleſia non in parietibus conſiſtit,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Jerom,</hi> in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 133. The Church is every where, <hi>ubi fides vera, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>You bring in St. <hi>Paul</hi> to ſay, (<hi>Rom.</hi> 1.8.) that the Roman Faith was preached in all the World: But you abuſe St. <hi>Paul,</hi> for 'tis not ſaid preached; nor is it ſaid Roman Faith. Their Faith was ſpoken of (as his courſe was to commend and encourage the faithful in every place) St. <hi>Paul</hi> intending to impart to them ſome ſpiritual gift, for they were not then eſtabliſhed: He only commended then the Faith of the Saints then in <hi>Rome</hi> (which they had newly received) <hi>viz.</hi> the Chriſtian Faith (never called it the Roman Faith) and ſo much he ſpake, and more, of the Faith of other Nations and Perſons to whom he wrote, and yet never any Nation or Perſon uſurped a Stile was never given them. St. <hi>Paul, Theſſ.</hi> 1.8. witneſſeth that, <hi>From the Church of</hi> Theſſalonica <hi>ſounded out the Word of the Lord, and in every place the Faith of the Theſſalonians was ſpread abroad; and were enſamples to all that believe, &amp;c.</hi> ver. 7. ibid. (which was a true Faith) and yet they never nick-named the Univerſal Chriſtian Church Theſſalonian, nor did they ever arrogantly and audaciouſly adopt the Univerſal Church of Chriſt as their own Off-ſpring and Iſſue, (or that they only were the Catholick) as <hi>Rome</hi> doth in your Poſition. St. <hi>Paul</hi> did commend the Faith then in <hi>Rome,</hi> but now 'tis changed and not worthy commendation. You ſay that is St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97402:14"/>why not St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Faith; was not his as good, and the other Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles the ſame that St. <hi>Peter</hi> taught? Was there no true Faith but what came from <hi>Rome?</hi> (and 'tis yet a queſtion whether St. <hi>Peter</hi> was ever there, <hi>Rome</hi> could never yet make it appear) Was all the Doctrine of the other Apoſtles invalid? Was not their power equal? (<hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19, 20. and 18.18. <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.22, 23.) 'Tis moſt ſure one was not above another (as before is proved) Chriſts Word was delivered to all to Preach; from which our very greateſt Adverſary is forced to confeſs, <hi>Summa Poteſtas Eccleſiaſtica non ſolum data eſt Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tro ſed etiam aliis Apoſtolis,</hi> (Bellarm. li. de Ro. Pont. ca. 1.) all are Supreme: Then they who pretend to be St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Succeſſors, have not Supreme Eccleſiaſtical Power any more than the Succeſſors of the other Apoſtles; for St. <hi>Auguſt. (Tract.</hi> 50. in St. <hi>Jo.</hi>) ſaith, <hi>Si hoc</hi> Petro <hi>tantum dictum eſt non facit hoc Eccleſia. The Keys were given to</hi> St. Peter <hi>and all the reſt in a Figure of the Church (as one ſaith) to whoſe power and to whoſe uſe they were given;</hi> not to one to Lord it over the reſt: <hi>It ſhall not be ſo with you,</hi> &amp;c. (as before.) And St. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin, (de Agon. Chri. ca.</hi> 30.) <hi>Petrus Perſonam Eccleſiae Catholicae ſuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, &amp; huic datae ſunt Claves quum</hi> Petro <hi>datae,</hi> ſo the Power is in the Catholick Church, not any ſingle Perſon, as is evident by the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the Primitive Church many hundred years after Chriſt, when was no Univerſal Biſhop (as before is proved) to St. <hi>Gregory</hi>'s time. St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Faith, not his Perſon, is the Rock againſt which, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for afterwards to his Perſon Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Get thee behind me, Satan,</hi> &amp;c. And a Temptation did too much prevail on him when he moſt hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribly fell in a perſonal and ſhameful denial of his Maſter (which coſt him many bitter Tears.) <hi>Epiphanius, (li.</hi> 2. <hi>Hereſ.</hi> 59.) tells us 'tis his Faith, <hi>Super hanc</hi> Petram <hi>ſolidae Fidei edificabo Eccleſiam meam:</hi> So St. <hi>Greg. Nyſſen</hi> alſo, <hi>Haec ſides Eccleſiae fundamentum eſt (de Trin. adver. Judaeos.)</hi> The ſame Interpretation gives St. <hi>Hilar. (li. de Trin.) Super hanc igitur confeſſionis</hi> Petram <hi>Eccleſiae edificatio eſt.</hi> And this Faith the whole Catholick Church hath, which is the Rock againſt which Hell Gates ſhall not prevail, to cauſe the Church to fail fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentally.</p>
                  <p>If any were ſupreme why not the beloved Diſciple, to whom it was never ſaid, <hi>Get thee behind me Satan,</hi> and who never denyed his Maſter: Or St. <hi>Paul,</hi> though none of the twelve, yet an Apoſtle for whom there is more colour, for <hi>He had the Right Hand of Fellowſhip
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97402:15"/>given him, Gal.</hi> 2.9. And he himſelf owned expreſly an Authority, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.17. <hi>And ſo ordain I in all Churches.</hi>—In all Churches, in the Roman as well as other (if <hi>Rome</hi> was then a Church.) <hi>Sollicitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do omnium Eccleſiarum, The Care of all the Churches,</hi> he ſaith, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28. And where was St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Supremacy, yea where was his Infallibility, when St. <hi>Paul</hi> rebuked and oppoſed him to his face, in that <hi>He walked not uprightly according to the Truth of the Goſpel? (Gal.</hi> 11.3.4.) And where was his Supremacy when he was ſent on Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rands by the Church, <hi>viz.</hi> by the other Apoſtles, <hi>Acts</hi> 11.3, 4. and <hi>Acts</hi> 15.13. And how can St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s pretended Succeſſors claim a Supremacy, that St. <hi>Peter</hi> had not himſelf. If any ſucceeded our Lord in the Principality of the Church, <hi>Epiphanius</hi> twice tells you it is St. <hi>James</hi> the Lords Brother; <hi>Ille primus Epiſcopalem Cathedram cepit, quum ei ante caeteros omnes, ſuum in terris Thronum Dominus tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didiſſet,</hi> (Epiphan. l. 3. Haereſ. 78. Page 103.)</p>
                  <p>You go on and ſay, <hi>What Faith the Romans had then, the very ſame they have at this preſent, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Not ſo neither, for <hi>Rome</hi> was a right Church, and is now a wrong; Their Faith is changed, at leaſt what Faith they have now, they had not then; the true Church then (and many hundred years after) knew not your preſent Errors and Superſtitions, not your prayer (in the Church) in an unknown Tongue, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſeth, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. The Church owned no ſupreme Prelate, no Pope above his fellows, uſurping a power to depoſe Princes, no worſhipping of Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, no invocation of Saints, no adoration of the Bread in Sacrament, no breaking of Chriſts Inſtitution in the Euchariſt, giving the holy Sacrament but in one kind, no Purgatory, no Decretal Epiſtles and Canons againſt Scripture to be believed as Scripture, <hi>No Doctrine of Devils, &amp;c. Tim.</hi> 4.1, 2, 3.</p>
                  <p>St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> (whoſe memory is honoured through the whole Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian world in all Churches) was of the true Catholick Church, no man will deny, and yet he was no Romaniſt in Opinion; for he was in the ſeparation of the Affrick Church from <hi>Rome,</hi> with many other Biſhops, and died therein. <hi>Ergo,</hi> 'tis poſſible to be of the true Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, and yet out of the Roman.</p>
                  <p>We are taught by St. <hi>Auguſt. (de Bap. con. Don. ca.</hi> 4.) <hi>Evident Scripture before all things muſt take place,</hi> for it is, as your own man, <hi>Stapleton,</hi> confeſſeth, (<hi>Relict. con.</hi> 4. <hi>q. Ar.</hi> 3.) the Foundation and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97402:15"/>Pillar of Faith: <hi>(Scripturam Fundamentum eſſe &amp; Columnam Fidei fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temur)</hi> Then I ſhall not eaſily be led away from the Foundation by the ſubtle tradition of men, ſeeing St. <hi>Paul</hi> gives more warning (<hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſ.</hi> 2.8.) <hi>Beware leſt any man ſpoil you through Philoſophy and vain De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, after the Tradition of men.</hi> Now what my Faith is I have told you in the beginning of my firſt Paper, which I take to be the Faith of the preſent Church of <hi>England.</hi> I embrace the Faith which the Apoſtles delivered, I believe the holy Scripture and the Creeds, and theſe in the ſence of the ancient Primitive Church: I ſubmit in all humility to the four great General Councils, (ſo much magnified throughout Chriſtendom) their Determinations and Interpretations; and I do believe all points of Doctrine generally received, as funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental in the Church of Chriſt. This I confeſs and ſubſcribe to, and ſeeing I ſo do, you are bound in charity to believe me, for you have all the proof that can be had, or that ever Man or Church required. Now ſhew me where I do depart from the Foundation, and yet I am no Papiſt, or ſhew me (if you can) where the Church of <hi>England</hi> doth fail in any one point fundamental in the Faith.</p>
                  <p>We do not, <hi>Hominis conſuetudinem ſequi ſed Dei veritatem,</hi> as St. <hi>Cypr. (l.</hi> 2. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 3.) teacheth, for <hi>Conſuetudo ſine veritate vetuſtas eſt Erroris,</hi> ibid.</p>
                  <p>We are bid to go to the <hi>Law and the Teſtimony; The Word is a Light unto our Feet, and Lanthorn to our Paths:</hi> we are taught to <hi>Search the Scripture, which is able to make the man of God perfect,</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Paul.</hi>) It was proclaimed from Heaven by God the Father firſt at <hi>Jordan,</hi> then at Mount <hi>Tabor, This is my well beloved Son, in whom I am well pleaſed, hear ye him;</hi> and to hear him is Life: And I know, <hi>They com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted two Evils that forſook the Fountain of Living Waters, to hew out to themſelves Ciſterns, broken Ciſterns that can hold no water,</hi> Jer. 2.13.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>That Epiſcopal and Kingly Government are inſeparable in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>and the Eſtabliſhment of both are,</hi> Jure Divino.</head>
               <p>WE have in the late Tragical Revolutions been too ſeverely taught, that no Project of Government either in Church or State, Epiſcopacy excluded, is conſiſtent with <hi>England</hi>'s happineſs;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97402:16"/>and that Epiſcopacy and Monarchy are inſeparable, and the only props of this Nations Peace, we, by the ſame cruel Experience have been made ſenſible; whereby it appears that 'tis <hi>England</hi>'s great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt to uphold both for her ſafety, and that the one cannot ſubſiſt without the other, was well underſtood by that ſecond <hi>Solomon,</hi> King <hi>James</hi> of bleſſed memory, from whom we have the Maxim (in his <hi>Baſil. Do.) Sublato Epiſcopo tollitur Rex, no Biſhop, no King:</hi> And no Faction or Profeſſion (though nick-naming themſelves Proteſtants) deviating from the Principles in Doctrine, and Practiſe in Worſhip, from the preſent Church of <hi>England,</hi> can ſtand with Monarchy. A right Proteſtant of the Engliſh Church, proteſts not only againſt the errors of <hi>Rome,</hi> but againſt all Schiſm and errors of every Sect, and againſt all Doctrine not agreeing with the Primitive Profeſſion, and Practiſe of the antient Church of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>There are ſorts of People that are ever clamorous, and deſigning to Reform the Reformed, and even to amend Reformation it ſelf, chiefly plotting a great alteration (which is more than a Reformation) of Church Government, by removal of Biſhops from the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but theſe are enemies to good Reformation, for no good Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>former ever held Epiſcopacy unlawful, the Order doth <hi>emanare ab Apoſtolis.</hi> The Government is of Divine Right, of which Chriſt himſelf (the <hi>Great High-Prieſt, Heb.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 14. and <hi>Biſhop</hi>) laid the Foundation, was Biſhop over all, and the Apoſtles were Miniſters; After him every Apoſtle had his Charge, many of them a Dioceſs, and was Overſeer, that is, Biſhop over many Churches, and they left this way of Government a Pattern for all Poſterity to follow. So it is manifeſt that Church-Government by Biſhops is as old (and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally practiſed) as Chriſtian Religion, and Chriſtian Faith was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in <hi>England</hi> ſoon after the Crucifixion of our Saviour, and the Government of the Church by Biſhops entred with it, as well it ought; for there was no other Government, Order, or Conſtitution in the Primitive Church: Apoſtles, Angels, Biſhops, Patriarchs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are <hi>Synonima,</hi> one Office under ſeveral Denominations. St. <hi>Paul</hi> an Apoſtle, <hi>not of men, neither by man, but by God,</hi> was a great <hi>Apoſtle</hi> or <hi>Biſhop: Timothy</hi> had a Juriſdiction over the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> and was ordained Biſhop (<hi>Tim.</hi> 3.22.) and ſo was <hi>Titus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Creet,</hi> and had many Miniſters under them. Thus entred Epiſcopacy and that Order of Prieſthood to the Government of the Church in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97402:16"/>There was an order of Prieſthood in the old Law, of which the high Prieſt was chief, and there were Prieſts and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites: ſo in the new it ſeemed meet to the Eternal Builder of the Church to leave, (by the example ſet by his Apoſtles) an Order and Method of Government therein; and this divine Emanation the Univerſal Church hath in all Ages embraced, and this Order beſt keeps the Presbyters and Clergy in Unity one with another, and in an Union of Doctrine and Worſhip in the Church through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, which otherwiſe, the order of Church-Diſcipline left to every Presbyter's private fancy to uſe after his own modelling, would greatly hazard the introducing as many Novels (may be Schiſms and Factions) as there are parochial Churches in the Land; what a Medly! what a Confuſion! what a <hi>Hydra!</hi> what a <hi>Babel!</hi> what an open Mockery as it were, of God would there be throughout the Nation to the ſcandal thereof; ſo the Church in <hi>England</hi> would have no appearance, no face and conſtant dreſs to be known by; Strangers would be at a loſs for the true Engliſh Church, finding here a <hi>Hydra</hi> of many faces not one like another.</p>
               <p>But who, and what generation of men, are wiſer and more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly than the Apoſtles and Fathers of old, to ſet up a new way of Government (of their own contriving) in Chriſt's Church? what Power on Earth can abrogate that Government by divine Inſtitution reared, and continued by the ſame right all Ages in the Church of God? And what neceſſity is here of a change or alteration of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in the Church from that which is Apoſtolical to that which peradventure may prove Diabolical? for what good can be expected by pulling down that which is of Gods ſetting up and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troducing a new (we know not what) of Man's abſolute deviſing? But if perchance, any Irregularities have crept in, or undue pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices, contrary to the eſtabliſhed Order, have been committed in any part of this Government which ſhould call for (or miniſter a Neceſſity of) Reformation; ſurely not unhallowed hands of the prophane Laity (who ſhould be governed by the Church and not the Church corrected by them) are fit Inſtruments of this Work, eſpecially in a Nation that hath ſo lately felt the dire Effects and Iſſues of a popular (pretended) Reformation, and wherein thoſe men have ſhown to the World what ill Workmen they are. Let the people reform their own Manners; This reforming part of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97402:17"/>what is amiſs in the Church belongs only to them to whom the Holy Spirit ſaid, <hi>I will be with you always to the end of the World;</hi> with the Church, <hi>i. e.</hi> with the Apoſtles, (whoſe perſonal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance laſted not in the World) and their Succeſſors in the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Apoſtles, Biſhops, Paſtors, Patriarchs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the Church, <hi>who ſhall have the aſſiſtance of the Holy Spirit for ever, As my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſent me ſo ſend I you:</hi> And as Chriſt ſent them ſo they ſent o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; <hi>ſo what ſhall ſeem meet to the Holy Spirit and to them</hi> whom Chriſt hath ſent and <hi>through whoſe word we are to believe in Chriſt,</hi> (St. <hi>Jo.</hi> 17.20.) the Governours of the Church ſucceſſively, to whom Chriſt hath promiſed to be with, and in whom only the <hi>Jus Divinum</hi> remains, may reform and alter what they judge conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient; for it is of the ſame power that chang'd the Sabbath from the laſt to the firſt day of the week, and 'tis from and by the ſame Power and Divine Authority that the Church conveys all the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, Sacraments and Holy things of God to his People from Generation to Generation. Theſe Paſtors and Governours with whom Chriſt according to his word is always preſent to the end of the World may (I grant) transfer the Government (ſhould they deem a neceſſity) into more hands, under other names than that of Biſhop; which (note) will ſtill be but Epiſcopacy degenerated into another denomination, the Power will be the ſame, not alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but tranſlated from one to many, in whom the Supremacy and <hi>Jus Divinum</hi> will remain: In all this the Church loſeth not her Right; But to take away the Government by Biſhops from the Church, without her Authority or Conſent, is to cut off great part of her ſelf, and to deprive her of much of her Being; And for Lay-men to encroach upon her Government and force it from her, is to rifle her of her Divine Right devolved to her as aforeſaid. The Authority came not from the Laity, ſo they have nothing to do therewith, and no Authority to diſturb it: For who can touch the Ark of God (though in their Judgment it ſhould ſeem to totter) and be guiltleſs, when <hi>Uzziah</hi>'s indiſcreet Zeal was ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely puniſhed? and what miſery did ſuch miſguided popular Zeal lately bring on this Nation in rudely medling with God's Ark, the Church, and pulling down that Government and thoſe Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours they ſhould Religiouſly have obeyed; And if <hi>Uzzah</hi>'s fault (whoſe fervent Zeal was to uphold not overthrow the Ark) was
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:97402:17"/>followed with ſo great deſtruction on his body, what puniſhment may they from Divine Juſtice expect who through Malice, Ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice and Ambition, ſeek to deſtroy the Government and Authority of the ancient Church of God?</p>
               <p>Think not then, Oh thou perverſe Enemy of the Apoſtolical Government of Gods Church, that your expectation of a change in this Age can have any foundation; that they who enact juſt Laws can propoſe unjuſt things to be enacted, that any one Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the whole Community, any one of the Repreſentatives of us Lay-men in this Lay-Parliament will adventure to lay violent hands on the Church of Chriſt, by endeavouring to pull down her Governours from their Seat to lay her deſolate, to bid defiance to the Spouſe of Chriſt, and ſo make War again, againſt the Soul of the Lords anoynted; for rothing can paſs into a Law but by Royal Aſſent, and what unhallowed Lip dare offer at a motion ſavouring of aboliſhing that radieated Government which his Majeſty, not only by his Education and choice hath received, and (following the Wiſdom and Piety of his Forefathers and Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors) hath approved and confirmed as moſt Catholick and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred, but obliged by ſolemn and ſacred Tie of an Oath at his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation to preſerve and maintain with all the Legal Rights of the Church. Who can be ſo impious to lay a ſnare for his precious Soul, or ſo vile to imagine to prevail in endeavouring to wheadle him to ſo great a Tranſgreſſion as the horrid ſin of Perjury, and to betray his Mother the Church to be worried again by her inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate Enemies, and ſo conſequently himſelf at laſt to be at the diſcretion and mercy of the ſame Gang, who have been as ready to unhinge the State as unſettle the Church, and do aſſuredly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the one from the other, that 'tis more than likely the old De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign is now a new on foot; for every ſtroke that hurts the Church doth wound the State.</p>
               <p>It would be ſtrange and ſavour much of Sataniſm if any ſhould adviſe a Son from inheriting his Fathers Virtues, to ſet at nought the Holy Counſel of ſo great a Saint in Heaven, not to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the pious Injunctions and Admonitions of a Religious King and Father, whoſe dying Speeches, as if he had bequeathed his Piety and Religion, his Zeal and Honour for the Church to be a Portion for his Children and a Glory to the Crown in his Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97402:18"/>obliged the Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> (our preſent Sovereign) by a ſweet invitation of Reaſon and Righteouſneſs to ſtand firm to the Religion in which he was educated; amongſt his admirable Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, divine Admonitions and Advices he ſaith — <hi>Above all, I would have you, as I hope you are already, well grounded and ſettled in your Religion: The beſt Profeſſion of which I have eſteemed that of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>in which you have been Educated: Yet I would have your Judgment and Reaſon now Seal to that Sacred Bond which Education hath written, that it may be judicially your own Religion, and not other men's Cuſtom or Tradition which you profeſs. In this I charge you to perſevere, as coming neareſt to God's Word for Doctrine, and to the primitive examples for Government.</hi> And in another place he adds: <hi>I do require and intreat you as your Father and your King, that you never ſuffer your heart to receive the leaſt check againſt, or diſaffection from the true Religion eſtabliſhed in the Church of</hi> England. <hi>I tell you I have tried it, and after much ſearch and many Diſputes, have concluded it to be the beſt in the World; not only in the Community as Chriſtian, but alſo in the ſpecial notion as Reformed, keeping the middle way between the pomp of ſuperſtitions Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, and the meanneſs of fantaſtick Anarchy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now behold, Oh ye Enemies of the Reformed Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> yea all the World behold, the Profeſſion of this pure Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is confirmed to be the trueſt on Earth by the moſt ſignal and Authentick Proof under Heaven, a Proof that bears Majeſty, yea Divinity in it, 'tis deſcended from on High; Kings are Gods on Earth; The King, the moſt Sacred of Kings hath tried it, (<hi>and 'tis the Honour of a King to ſearch out a Matter, Prov.</hi> 25.2.) God's Vicegerent made it the great Buſineſs and work of his Life to ſearch for Truth and pure Profeſſion of Religion, and in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverting confounded all the Arguments and Argumentators a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God's Church, to their Amazement and Confuſion. He in the Deciſion would not part with one jot of Truth to betray or oppreſs the Church: <hi>His Righteouſneſs he held faſt and would not let it go, Job.</hi> 26.6. for when he was in the cruel hands of his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable Enemies (oven a Captive at their diſpofal) at <hi>New-Caſtle,</hi> far from the Aid of good Men or Books to aſſiſt and comfort him, at this diſadvantage (as if God had delivered him as he did <hi>Job</hi> to be buffeted by Satan, and winnowed) their great Champion of their
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97402:18"/>new Goſpel, Dr. <hi>H.</hi> the deputed Tempter of the Synod and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons Houſe, furniſhed with all the enſnaring Arguments Sedition and Treaſon could invent, was ſent to captivate the Soul of his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, and ruffle him out of his Faith (thereby to lay a ſtone for their new <hi>Babel</hi>) but met with ſuch Divine and convincing Reaſons from the King, who ſo conciſely and ſweetly anſwered every point of their long ſtudied and tedious Sophiſms, as overcame the Giant and all his Hoſt of ſophiſtrated Arguments, that returning in high diſcontent to thoſe who ſent him, in great diſcompoſure of Spirit furiouſly cryed out, <hi>Never man ſpake as the King ſpake, and argued as the King argued, he is able to confound ye all, &amp;c.</hi> and being enraged that he was van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed, fell into a Conflict of Spirit, and not long after finiſhed his days. Kings repreſent God, are Children of the Moſt High, <hi>Sit upon Gods Throne;</hi> the King hath tryed it, (and where was there ever, or can be found on earth, a Prince, for Piety, Religion, and Wiſdom, his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual, or one like him) and who can be more concern'd for a Child than a Father, for a People than their King? The King hath tri'd it, and whom can we truſt but thoſe that have tried? and whom can a Child bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter truſt than a Father? and whom can we, a People, better truſt than the Father of our Country, our King, a Nurſing Father, who had no end but the ſalvation of his Child, the ſalvation of his People, and to preſerve them from Apoſtacy in the time of Tryal and Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution they might meet with? A King, who was able to try, labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in the ſearch, judicious to diſcern, and moſt wiſe and learned to judge, who took care of us all as for his own ſoul, was faithful (before the Lord) unto the death, preferring his Religion before his Crowns and Life, the Church and his People before his own ſafety; no torment inflicted on his Body, could make a Conqueſt of his Soul, for his unvanquiſhed Fortitude after many hard Conflicts, bitter Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions and Indignities heaped on him, witneſſed the truth of the holy Faith and Religion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> by giving up his Life for the ſame, ſo imitating his Saviour, ſubſcribed and ſigned the Truth with his laſt blood.</p>
               <p>Kings are Divinely inſpired (as by the Actions and Writings of this Holy One is ſufficiently evidenced) <hi>The Eyes of God are with Kings on their Throne,</hi> Job. 36.7. <hi>The King is an Angel of God to diſcern good and bad,</hi> 2 Sam. 14.17, 20. <hi>An Angel of Light;</hi> and to whom then ſhould we repair for Righteous Judgment, but to him who ſees
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:97402:19"/>with Gods byes, <hi>to the Angel of Light, to the Light of</hi> Iſrael, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Isiah.</hi> 8.19. Never was there a Teſt in any Age or Nation like it, what doubt can there be of the purity and truth of the Profeſſion, but that every man may ſafely take and ſubſcribe to our Religion upon this Tryal, and Centre his Truſt upon this Teſtimony and Evidence, and Author it here for ever? What better proof can the whole World produce? Is it not worth ten thouſaend? 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.3.</p>
               <p>Yet not wholly to take it upon the truſt of others, and be led to implicitheſs, barely to take our Profeſſion of Religion from <hi>other mens Cuſtom or Tradition</hi> (as he ſaid) this good King hath given us a light, and marked us out a way to confirm our ſelves in it, to make it our own by Election, in weighing it with ſound Reaſon and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (though hodietter Leſſons than) from his Divine Truths and Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony can be offered to the World) and ſo hath put us to School to the moſt Choice, Learned, Religious, and Rational Treatiſes of holy Churchmen upon the point; that we muſt acknowledg, though we are owing to Education for initiating and firſt Principling us in our Religion, we are wholly owing to his Directions, convincing Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Divine Teſtimony for the Confirmation of us in it; in it, in the beſt Religion in the world, which he hath taken by Divine Inſpiration from above, not ſole Infuſion beneath, by Revelation from Heaven, not Education; Seducement, or Cuſtom on Earth; and Heaven it ſelf hath hallowed and approved it, by the late miraculous replanting the ſame Profeſſion of Religion and Faith in this Land, and reſtoring the Royal Defender thereof in peace. Hope not then (Oh thou full of wicked Imaginations) that any Branch of that Royal and Holy Stem can be of any other Religion than the beſt in the world, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the Reformed Religion profeſſed and eſtabliſhed in the Church of <hi>England, Thou ſhalt not Revile the Gods, nor ſpeak evil of the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of thy People, Exod.</hi> 2.21 <hi>Acts</hi> 23. Think not then that any Child of ſo pious and ſacred a Parent, can deſpiſe the Admonition of an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of Light, (and his Book as Heretical) and abandon that Religion the beſt Religion ſo recommended, ſo proved, and the Truth thereof ſo confirmed, but will Religiouſly obſerve ſuch Divine Admonitions and Holy Injunctions, and will <hi>Bind them for a Sign upon his Hands, and to the as Frontlets between his Eyes,</hi> always before him, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. that it may be well with him for ever; and not by following ſtrange Gods, and thoſe ways he was warned to avoid and beware of, Rob
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:97402:19"/>the dead, the moſt innocent dead, his Royal Father, of the Glory of his Sufferings, of his Crown of Martyrdom; for this were to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweeten the memory of the pureſt Innocence (next the Saviour of the world) that ever was born of a Woman. This were (which is a moſt malitious wickedneſs but to imagine) not only to Countenance his Enemies cruelty that murthered his Body, but more barbarouſly againſt all Humanity and bonds of Nature to crucifie his Honour, to ſlay his everlaſting Name and Memory, to render him Inglorious, his Death a Reproach, to defile his Sacred Duſt, to raiſe a Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt him in his Grave worſe than all the ſmarts and horrid ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of his Life, to render his Religion (that Religion which he wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred with his Blood) a Hereſie, and himſelf a moſt grand Heretick, ſo conſequently to die deſervedly, and the deſtruction of him and his faithful Subjects (in defence of him and the Church) to be Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous; as if his Enemies depriving him of his Crowns on Earth, were not ſufficient, but his dear Off-ſpring to raviſh from him alſo that which he hath in Glory; to help the Popiſh and Phanatick Enemies to dethrone a Saint, and unſaint a Martyr that is Canoniz'd in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, to pull him from thence, and as much as in them lies to tear his precious Name out of the Book of Life; to make blacker his days on Earth, than all the malice of his Enemies could ever make it, to take his bleſſed Memory out of the Kalendar of Time, to eraze it out of the Rubrick, to repeal and make ſcandalous the Statute of the Realin that hath ordained his day, his day of Glory, his day of ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings for the Church (the Thirtieth of <hi>January</hi>) to be obſerved for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; to raviſh his Name from the number of the Good and Vertuous on Earth, to take the Head of the grand Rebel, <hi>O. C.</hi> from the Pole of Infamy, and to rank that Uſurpers Bones again amongſt the Shrines of Kings, and even to marble his Herſe into a Statue amongſt the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies of <hi>England.</hi> But never can the bleſſed Name and Honour of Holy <hi>Charles</hi> be thus ſtormed, whilſt the Earth ſhall bear any Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor on the Britiſh Throne, deſcended from his ſacred Loyns, and <hi>God</hi> grant his Race to Sway the Scepter, may be as laſting as the Sun and Moon. —<hi>Repent therefore</hi> (Oh thou Diſſenter from all Charity and Goodneſs) <hi>of this thy wickedneſs, and pray God, if perhaps the thought of thine heart may be forgiven thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No Inſidel that had ſeen the Finger of God in the late great Reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Church and State, but would have embraced the Faith of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:97402:20"/>the Church of <hi>England</hi> in the Notion and Manner as Religion is here Eſtabliſhed upon the account of the Miracle only, as may well be concluded from that credible Relation given of a great Prince or Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zier in the Ottoman Territories, who hearing the Story of the Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious Miracle of reſtoring the King of <hi>England</hi> to his People, and the Proteſtant Religion to the Nation, even the ſudden Redemption from Baniſhment, and returning the Captivity of Church and People in peace, in the midſt of Armies without bloodſhed, was ſtartled into an Amazement and holy Rapture, and in the high Tranſport paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately cryed out; <hi>Oh had I the happineſs to be acquainted with that bleſſed Prince, His Religion ſhould be my Religion, His God ſhould be my God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is no new thing that Miracles have Converted Nations, but 'tis a ſtrange thing that there ſhould be ſo ſtupid and benummed a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Men in any Nation, whom Miracles move not, even this wondring of the <hi>Mahumetan</hi> (like <hi>Nebuchadnezzar, Dan.</hi> 3.29. <hi>There is no other God can deliver after this ſort</hi>) in a holy Reverence to this power of the Almighty, and work of his Mercy; is a kind of Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the God of the Proteſtants of <hi>England,</hi> and as much as in him lies, an embracing of the Faith in his Heart.—Can then any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian of <hi>England</hi> forget theſe <hi>Magnalia Caeli,</hi> (or forſake that Faith, Doctrine, Worſhip, and Diſcipline, which not the Arm of Fleſh, but the Might of Providence hath ſo amazingly Replanted and Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred in this Land) and be good?</p>
               <p>This Profeſſion of the Church of <hi>England</hi> is apparently owned by God himſelf to be his own Church, for lately taking of his Rod of Correction, and, in his good time, ceaſing Chaſtiſing his People, whom he for their ſins had afflicted; he diſſipated all Sects from Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and every Religion from Eſtabliſhment, but that which he call'd back from Captivity, which he Redeemed from Thraldom to Liberty; and to him who continued his Faith, he reſtored his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms; for the ſake of the Church he re-Inthron'd the King in his Rights, and for the ſake of the King he re-Eſtabliſhed the Church.</p>
               <p>Oh the Majeſty and Divinity of Kings, whoſe Government is Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by God himſelf! <hi>By me Kings Reign, &amp;c. Diadema Regis in manu Dei, Iſa.</hi> 62.3. <hi>The Lord doth ſet the Crown upon the Kings head, Pſal.</hi> 21.3. Kings are of Gods ſetting up, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 9.10, 17. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.24. <hi>See ye him whom the Lord hath choſen,</hi> and ought not to be of
<pb facs="tcp:97402:20"/>the Peoples pulling down. They are <hi>Chriſti Domini, the Lords A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed, Touch not mine Anointed, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>who can ſtretch forth his Hand againſt the Lords Anointed, and be guiltleſs?</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26.9. Every mans right, the property of every Engliſh Man is preſerved to him by the Law, <hi>per Magnum Chartam Anglia,</hi> ſo the Right of Kings is conveyed and confirmed to them by the great Charter of Heaven, an indelible Law (greater than that of the Medes and Perſians) that no man may preſume to attempt to alter: Kings have their Titles from above, and hold their Kingdoms under God, for all Kingdoms are his, (and not the Peoples) He eſtabliſhes Thrones and Kingdoms for ever, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.4, 5. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 29. <hi>v.</hi> 23.2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.13. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89. A King is more honoured than the Angels, hath Gods more peculiar Divine Stamp upon him, and is made the Son of God: <hi>I have choſen him to be my Son, and I will be his Father, Chron.</hi> 28.6. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.14. And who can without higheſt Rebellion to the King of Heaven, attempt to deface this holy Stamp, by approaching to hurt Gods Son and Vicegerent, in Office or Perſon. The Perſons of Kings are ſacred, inveſted with Divinity, which ſtrike an Awe on all good men: This <hi>David,</hi> when a Subject, well knew and felt, and Adored the Divinity; <hi>David,</hi> the moſt undaunted Courage of the Earth, the great Champion of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> whom no danger could affright, that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countred the mighty <hi>Goliah</hi> in the Head of the puiſſant Army of the Philiſtins, was the moſt Valiant of the World, that ſlew his ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, yet when his King (though a ſingle Perſon) became his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and ſought his Life (cauſeleſly) to take it away, he could not lift up a hand againſt his Perſon, when it ſeemed eaſie to have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed him in the Cave; dread fell upon <hi>David,</hi> and his heart ſmote him but for cutting off the Skirt of <hi>Saul</hi>'s Garment, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.5. and ſaid, <hi>The Lord forbid that I ſhould do this thing unto my Maſter, the Lords Anointed, to ſtretch forth mine Hand againſt him, ſeeing he is the Anointed of the Lord, v.</hi> 6.10. And <hi>David,</hi> though he knew he was to ſucceed <hi>Saul</hi> in the Throne, and be King after him, and had a ſecond opportunity to have been avenged of his Enemy <hi>Saul,</hi> (who again purſued after his Life) and might have ſlain him in his Trench, and put to the Sword his whole Guard of Armed Men whilſt they lay ſleeping, yet he became afraid to unſheath a Sword againſt his Enemy to cut him off, and would not permit any man to hurt the <hi>Lords Anointed,</hi> but ſaved him from danger, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26.9, 11. Yea
<pb facs="tcp:97402:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſharply robuked the Kings Guards for being no more watchful over their Charge, telling them what they, for their Careleſneſs juſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved: <hi>Ye are worthy to die, becauſe ye have not kept your Maſter the Lords Anointed, v.</hi> 16.</p>
               <p>Now to eſcape meriting this Sentence of <hi>David,</hi> let all Engliſh Spirits unite in a vigilant Care to preſerve his Sacred Majeſty, our Royal Maſter, the <hi>Lords Anointed,</hi> the Protector and Defender of us all; Let every good Subject and Son of the Reformed Church, the Proteſtant Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſtill <hi>Fear God and Honour the King, and meddle not with them that are given to change, Prov.</hi> 24.21. <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geat Eccleſia Anglicana verè Catholica, &amp; Vivat Rex</hi> Angliae <hi>Regum Proteſtantiſſimus; Exurgat Deus,</hi> And let the Enemies of both be for ever diſperſed. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:97402:21"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
